Henry Harley Arnold Papers
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress
Henry Harley Arnold Papers 1903-1963 1940-1946
MSS11189
Arnold, Henry Harley, 1886-1950
160,000 items
249 containers plus 1 classified and 33 oversize
109 linear feet
269 microfilm reels
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress Washington, D.C.
Pioneer aviator and United States Army officer. Correspondence, memoranda, journals, notebooks, drafts and proofs of Henry Harley (Hap) Arnold's memoirs, Global Mission (1949), articles, speeches, reports, orders, printed material, photographs, and other papers relating chiefly to the development of military aeronautics in the United States and to aeronautical policies and events of World War II.
Selected Search Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the LC Catalog. They are grouped by name of person or organization, by subject or location, and by occupation and listed alphabetically.
People
Adamson, Hans Christian--Correspondence.; Andrews, Frank Maxwell, 1884-1943--Correspondence.; Arnold family.; Arnold, Henry Harley, 1886-1950.; Arnold, Henry Harley, 1886-1950. Global mission. 1949.; Baruch, Bernard M. (Bernard Mannes), 1870-1965--Correspondence.; Beebe, Eugene H. (Eugene Harold), 1906-1992--Correspondence.; Bell, Lawrence Dale, 1894-1956--Correspondence.; Bradley, Follett, 1890-1952--Correspondence.; Chamberlin, Jo Hubbard, 1905-1998. Jo Hubbard Chamberlin papers.; Craig, Malin, 1875-1945--Correspondence.; Doolittle, James Harold, 1896-1993--Correspondence.; Douglas, Donald W. (Donald Wills), 1892-1981--Correspondence.; Eaker, Ira, 1896-1987--Correspondence.; Eichelberger, Robert L.--Correspondence.; Eisenhower, Dwight D. (Dwight David), 1890-1969--Correspondence.; Elliott, J. E. (Joseph E.)--Correspondence.; Giles, Barney McKinney, 1892-1984--Correspondence.; Harmon, Millard Fillmore, 1888-1945--Correspondence.; Harris, Arthur Travers, Sir, 1892-1984--Correspondence.; Hungerford, Charles Frederick Algernon Portal, Viscount Portal of, 1893-1971--Correspondence.; Jouett, Jack.; Kindelberger, James Howard, 1895-1962--Correspondence.; King, Ernest Joseph, 1878-1956--Correspondence.; Kuter, Laurence Sherman, 1905- --Correspondence.; Lindbergh, Charles A. (Charles Augustus), 1902-1974--Correspondence.; Lovett, Robert A. (Robert Abercrombie), 1895-1986--Correspondence.; Magee, James M. (James McDevitt) 1877-1949--Correspondence.; Marshall, George C. (George Catlett), 1880-1959--Correspondence.; Martin, Glenn L. (Glenn Luther), 1886-1955--Correspondence.; Marx, Louis, 1896-1982--Correspondence.; Millikan, Robert Andrews, 1868-1953--Correspondence.; Northrop, John Knudsen, 1895-1981--Correspondence.; Pederson, Edwin--Correspondence.; Rickenbacker, Eddie, 1890-1973--Correspondence.; Shelmire, Horace Weeks, 1886-1965--Correspondence.; Spaatz, Carl, 1891-1974--Correspondence.; Stettinius, Edward R., Jr. (Edward Reilly), 1900-1949--Correspondence.; Vaughan, Guy W., 1884-1966--Correspondence.; Von Kármán, Theodore, 1881-1963--Correspondence.; Warner, Jack, Jr., 1916-1995--Correspondence.; Wright, Burdette S. (Burdette Shields), 1893-1961--Correspondence.; Wright, Orville, 1871-1948--Correspondence.; Wright, Wilbur, 1867-1912--Correspondence.
Organizations
Combined Chiefs of Staff (U.S. and Great Britain); Pan American Airways Corporation.; United States. Army Air Forces.; United States. Army. Air Corps.; United States. Joint Chiefs of Staff.
Subjects
Aeronautics, Commercial.; Aeronautics, Military.; Air mail service.; Flight training.; Flight.; Generals--United States--Biography.; Pearl Harbor (Hawaii), Attack on, 1941.; World War, 1939-1945--Aerial operations.; World War, 1939-1945--Campaigns--Alaska--Aleutian Islands.; World War, 1939-1945--Germany.
Places
Sonoma (Calif.)--Social life and customs.
Occupations
Army officers.; Aviators.
Acquisition Information
The papers of Henry Harley Arnold, pioneer aviator, general of the United States Army Air Forces, and author, were given to the Library by his wife, Eleanor Arnold, in 1951. The bulk of the Arnold Papers were placed in the Aeronautics Section of the Science and Technology Division of the Library in 1952 and 1953. A major addition was received from the Office of the Chief of Staff, United States Air Force, in 1957. Additions received between 1958 and 1999 include the Jo Chamberlin File processed in 1999. Custody of the collection was transferred to the Manuscript Division in 1960. A military mail log formerly separated from the collection was also added in 1999. An oversize scrapbook compiled by Edna M. Adkins and given by Hazel A. Garland and a formerly separated oversize statistical report were added to the collection in 2012.
Additional Guides
A description of the papers appears in an article by Marvin W. McFarland, The H. H. Arnold Collection, Library of Congress Quarterly Journal of Current Acquisitions, vol. ix, no. 4, Aug. 1952, pp. 171-181.
Access and Restrictions
The papers of Henry Harley Arnold are open to research. Researchers are advised to contact the Manuscript Reading Room prior to visiting. Many collections are stored off-site and advance notice is needed to retrieve these items for research use.
Security Classified Documents
Government regulations control the use of security classified items in this collection. Manuscript Division staff can furnish information concerning access to and use of classified items.
Microfilm
A microfilm edition of part of these papers is available on 269 reels. Consult a reference librarian in the Manuscript Division concerning availability for purchase or interlibrary loan.
Biographical Note
Date Event
1886, June 25 Born, Gladwyne, Pa.
1907 Graduated, United States Military Academy, West Point, N.Y. Commissioned second lieutenant in the infantry, United States Army
1907 1909 Served with the twenty-ninth infantry, the Philippines
1909 1911 Served with the twenty-ninth infantry, Governor's Island, N.Y.
1911 Taught to fly in ten days by Orville Wright, Dayton, Ohio Received military aviator's license number two
1911 1912 Flight instructor, Signal Corps Aviation School, College Park, Md., and Augusta, Ga.
1912 Awarded first Mackay trophy for a thirty-mile triangular reconnaissance flight First military aviator to use a radio for aerial observation of field artillery fire
1913 Married Eleanor A. Pool
1916 Served briefly with thirteenth infantry, the Philippines Served two months with third infantry, Madison Barracks, N.Y.
1916 1917 Returned to air service as a captain Supply officer, Aviation School, San Diego, Calif.
1917 Organized and commanded Seventh Aero Squadron, Panama Canal Zone
1917 1918 In charge of Information Service, Aviation Division, Signal Corps Assistant executive director, military aeronautics
1918 Executive officer and later assistant director, military aeronautics Inspected aviation activities in Europe
1919 District supervisor, Western District, Air Service, Rockwell Field, Coronado, Calif.
1919 1922 Originated and activated first army aerial forest fire patrol in Washington, Oregon, and California Air officer, Ninth Corps Area, San Francisco, Calif.
1922 1924 Commanding officer, Rockwell Air Depot, Coronado, Calif.
1925 Graduated, Army Industrial College, Washington, D.C. Obtained air mail charter from the postmaster general and organized Pan American Airways with Carl Spaatz,; Jack Jouett, and John Montgomery
1926 Published Airmen and Aircraft: An Introduction to Aeronautics (New York: Ronald Press. 216 pp.)
1926 1929 Commander, air squadron, Cavalry School, Fort Riley, Kans.
1928 Published Bill Bruce aviator series
1929 Graduated, Command and General Staff School, Ft. Leavenworth, Kans.
1929 1936 Commander, Fairfield and Dayton, Ohio, and March Field, Calif. Established Munroc Lake, Calif., bombing and gunnery range for early experiments in precision bombardment.
1933 1935 Supervised twenty-five Civilian Conservation Corps, March Field, Calif.
1934 Directed Western Division, Air Corps air mail service, Salt Lake City, Utah Awarded distinguished flying cross and second Mackay trophy for leading a mass flight of bombers from Washington, D.C., to Alaska
1936 Published with Ira Eaker This Flying Game (New York: Funk & Wagnalls. 275 pp.)
1936 1938 Assistant to chief of air corps, Washington, D.C.
1938 1942 Chief of air corps; acting deputy chief of staff for air, 1940
1941 Published with Ira Eaker Winged Warfare (New York: Harper & Bros. 265 pp.)
1941 1942 Chief of army air forces
1941 1945 Member, Joint and Combined Chiefs of Staff,; Arcadia (Newfoundland), post Arcadia (Washington, D.C.), Casablanca,; Quadrant, (Quebec, Canada), Sextant (Cairo, Egypt - Tehran, Iran), London,; Octagon (Quebec, Canada), and Terminal (Berlin, Germany) conferences
1942 Published with Ira Eaker Army Flyer (New York: Harper & Bros. 299 pp.)
1942 1946 Commanding general, army air forces Deputy chief of staff, army
1943 Promoted to general
1944 Named to five star rank of general of the army
1946 Assigned to duty in the Office of Chief of Staff, Washington, D.C. Retired from active duty to his ranch, Sonoma, Calif.
1949 Published Global Mission (New York: Harper & Bros. 626 pp.)
1950 Died, Sonoma, Calif.
Scope and Content Note
The papers of Henry Harley Arnold (1886-1950) span the years 1903 to 1967, with the bulk of the items concentrated in the years of World War II (1940-1946). The collection is large and contains material on almost all aspects of Arnold's adult life. The most comprehensive documentation, however, covers Arnold's tenure as chief of the United States Army Air Corps (1938-1942), chief of the army air forces (1941-1942), and commanding general of the army air forces (1942-1946). These changes in nomenclature reflect the growth of the military air arm from a small auxiliary of the army in the 1930s to a massive semi-autonomous armed service in World War II which became formally independent of the Army in 1947. Arnold, one of the nation's earliest military pilots, built what became the modern United States Air Force, and his papers are a documentation of that creation.
The papers are divided into a number of series and subseries. Several of the subseries contain detailed indexes which were prepared contemporaneously by Arnold's military staff or later by personal assistants either to Arnold or his wife, Eleanor Pool Arnold, after he left active service. In some cases, documents on the same or similar subjects are found in different subseries. When Arnold's papers arrived at Library of Congress, large sections came in an arrangement devised by Arnold and his staff during the creation and use of the papers. It was judged best not to modify Arnold's arrangement because it reflected Arnold's use of the papers and because several of these sections came with detailed indexes providing excellent research access to this material.
The Family Papers series, 1922-1955, consists largely of correspondence between Arnold and his family during the 1930s and 1940s. Most of this correspondence deals with family affairs along with some family business activities.
The Journals and Notebooks series, 1908-1946, includes a few journals that go back to Arnold's earliest flying days and the army air corps. Of significant interest are Arnold's notebooks from World War II when he took part in several of the major wartime conferences of the Allied leadership. Arnold kept notes on those meetings in small pocket diaries. These notes were later transcribed, and Arnold often interspersed with the typed transcriptions documents relating to the events noted in the journals. Arnold's notes include both substantive remarks about the issues discussed as well as observations about the principal figures at the conferences and physical aspects of the trip. Among the key wartime conferences recorded in Arnold's journals are those of Roosevelt and Churchill at Placentia Bay in 1941, the 1943 Cairo conferences with Roosevelt and Churchill, the Teheran conference with Stalin,; Churchill and Roosevelt, and the 1944 Roosevelt-Churchill conference at Quebec. Also present are journals Arnold kept for wartime inspection trips to Great Britain, China, North Africa and the Pacific theater.
The Correspondence series, 1907-1967, is divided into several subseries. The Chronological subseries consists largely of military correspondence, reports, memoranda, and other official documents. Among its earliest items are the 1911 reports of then Second Lieutenant Arnold on his training as a pilot by the Wright brothers aviation company. Also present are copies of letters from Wilbur and Orville Wright to Arnold in which the Wrights answer Arnold's technical questions about the aircraft the brothers were building for the army. By 1939 Arnold was a brigadier general in charge of America's growing but still small army air corps. His files for 1939 and 1940 are filled with reports by American military observers in Europe about the rapid evolution of German, French, and British aircraft and air warfare tactics under the pressure of combat. As one report noted, European fighter aircraft in 1940 were routinely equipped with guns whose firepower was several times that of existing American fighters. Under Arnold's command, America's military air arm quickly caught up with and then surpassed in lethality those of other nations. Present in Arnold's 1945 file is an 8 August 1945 report to him on the dropping of the atomic bomb that begins “ Hiroshima is no more.”
The Congratulatory and Condolence Letters subseries comprises files generally in chronological order for major events in Arnold's life.
The General Correspondence subseries is further divided into two parts. The first is an alphabetical file consisting largely of correspondence and other documents of a military or semiofficial nature from Arnold's World War II years, although correspondence about personal matters is also found. The second part of this subseries, a Serial file, 1946-1950, consists of files numbered 1 through 714. Access to these numbered files is provided by an index which lists personal names or private institutions with a designation of the numbered file in which relevant material can be found. The material in these files is a mixture of correspondence and other documents dealing with Arnold's professional and personal activities after his retirement.
The Personal Correspondence subseries includes material from the early 1930s and the period from 1943 to 1950. The material for 1930-1934 is largely professional correspondence dealing with aviation and army air corps activities. The files for 1943-1950 consists largely of documents dealing with Arnold's purchase and maintenance of a residential property in Sonoma, California, to which he retired after his World War II duties.
The Military File series is the largest in the collection and is extremely rich with material on all aspects of American military air activity in World War II: mobilization, organization, supply, weaponry, training, personnel, strategy, command, intelligence, and technology. Only the official records of the army air force exceed in abundance the resources offered by the Arnold papers for the study of American air warfare in World War II. Much of the material in the Military File series consists of copies of official records which can be found at the National Archives. What gives this collection research interest is that it consists of copies of those documents that Arnold or his staff regarded as of sufficient significance to cull from the flood of paper that passed through his office during World War II.
In the Military File, the first subseries, entitled the Decimal File, 1940-1945, consists of military documents, messages, correspondence, memoranda, and reports filed in accordance with a decimal filing system (similar to the Dewey decimal system) used by the army during World War II. Access to the material in these files in best sought by use of two card-file indexes. The first index is alphabetical by the name of an individual connected to the documents. The index gives the decimal files in which documents by or about that person can be found. The second index is alphabetical by subject, institution, or organization. The indexes are detailed, with the name index taking up containers 39-46 and the subject index containers 47-60. In addition to the decimal designation, some of the decimal files also have subject matter titles which have been included in the container listing of the Arnold Papers.
The Message File subseries consists of incoming and outgoing official cables and other messages between Arnold's headquarters and other offices during World War II. Most messages are filed alphabetically by subject, office, or the name of a frequent correspondent, Dwight Eisenhower, for example. This subseries also contains a chronological file of Arnold's incoming and outgoing messages filed under his name.
The Official File subseries includes military reports, memoranda, correspondence, and other documents designated by files numbered 1-287 and 516-540. Files 1-210 have subject matter titles in alphabetical order while files numbered 211-287 have geographic area titles in alphabetical order along with a few files for non-geographic military commands, ferrying command, for example. Files numbered 516-540 contain a variety of reports, logs, and extensive documentation deriving from the investigation of the Pearl Harbor attack and the role of the army air force in that disaster. Indexes are available for both of these numbered sequences. Files numbered 288-515 are not extant in the Arnold Papers.
The Reports subseries, 1913-1949, consists of official military reports related to air warfare topics. Some of the reports are printed or near-print reports while others are in manuscript form. General reports largely concern the overall status of American military air power. Specialized reports relate to a variety of topics, such as atomic energy, analytic studies of American air warfare campaigns during World War II, and estimates of German war potential.
The Subject File subseries, 1917-1950, deals with a wide variety of official, professional, and private matters, treating such diverse topics as “Elks in Mexico, ” regarding the fraternal order of Elks, military aircraft production, 1938-1945, and the 1941 Argentia conference of Allied leaders in Newfoundland. Most of the files deal with important military affairs during World War II.
The Miscellany subseries, 1934-1951, of the Military File series also contains a variety of files, including a chronological file of army air force air adjutant general memoranda and messages; a chronological mail log for Arnold's office listing “to,” “from,” and the subject of correspondence; a chronological file of Arnold's military correspondence spanning 1934-1945, the bulk of which is concentrated during World War II and deals with a wide variety of military topics; and an extensive chronological log of incoming telephone calls, often with notes on the subject of the call. In addition to the telephone logs, this subseries also includes a number of transcripts of telephone conversations between Arnold and members of his staff with other officials. Files of official war communiques publicly released by military offices relate to the course of the war effort. A Personal File index for files numbered 1-50 is included but only files numbered 34-40 and 42 are present in the collection.
The Postmilitary File, 1946-1949, contains Arnold's extensive correspondence after his retirement. The correspondence is divided into two sets, “A” and “B,” and is filed alphabetically. Indexes are provided for both sets. This series also contains subject matter files on the B-36 bomber, atomic testing, and congressional hearings on aviation policy.
The Speeches and Writings series, 1923-1955, includes Arnold's extensive speeches and writings, most of which relate to aviation and military matters. Arnold had a clear sense that he was taking part in the creation of a powerful American air arm, and many of his speeches and essays reflect his sensibility about the history-making character of the events he was discussing. Also in this series are files related to his 1949 book Global Mission, his memoir of the army air force in World War II.
Among the Miscellany series, 1903-1963, are photographs, financial papers, and biographical material, printed material, and other items that further reflect Arnold's historical sensitivity, especially the material he collected about the early years of American military aviation. Included are photographs, lists and biographies of early pilots, contemporaneous print and near-print accounts of important events in military aviation history, and extensive scrapbooks.
The Jo Chamberlin File, 1941-1989, consists of scrapbooks containing memoranda, reports, speeches, military papers, printed matter, and other miscellaneous material reflecting Chamberlin's assignment to the Office of Information Services, Army Air Forces, and as an aide to Arnold. Included are drafts of reports to the secretary of war by the commanding general, Army Air Forces, with annotations by Arnold, speeches drafted by Chamberlin for Arnold, reports from the Aleutian Island Campaign, information regarding 'foo-fighters,' and writings on Chamberlin's trip to Germany in the waning days of World War II.
The Classified series consists of security classified items removed from the collection. Removal sheets for all such material can be found in the files from which the items were removed. When any item in this series is declassified, it is restored to its original file. Classified items are not included on the microfilm edition of the Arnold Papers prepared in 1995.
Organization of the Papers
The collection is arranged in eleven series:
Family Papers, 1922-1955
Journals and Notebooks, circa 1908-1946
Correspondence, 1907-1967
Military File, 1913-1951
Postmilitary File, 1946-1949
Speeches and Writings, 1923-1955
Miscellany, 1903-1963
Military Mail Log, 1941-1945
Jo Chamberlin File, 1941-1989
Oversize, 1930-1955
Classified, 1932-1949
Container List
- Family Papers, 1922-1955 (Box 1-2, Reel 1-2)
  Correspondence between Arnold and family members; also includes newspaper clippings.
  Arranged alphabetically by type of material. Correspondence is further arranged alphabetically by family member.
  - Correspondence (Box 1, Reel 1)
    - Arnold, Cliff (brother), 1936-1945
    - Arnold, David Lee (son), 1941-1947
    - Arnold, Eleanor (wife), 1940-1955
    - Arnold, Henry Harley, Jr. (son), 1939-1945
    - Arnold, Herbert A. (father), 1922-1932
    - Arnold, Joseph Price (brother), 1939-1945
    - Arnold, Richard F. (nephew), 1939-1945
    - Arnold, Thomas (brother), 1939-1944
    - Arnold, Thomas H. (nephew), 1939-1942
    - Arnold, William Bruce (son), 1937-1945
    - Harley, Katharine V. (cousin), 1941-1946
    - Pool, J. Henry (brother-in-law), 1937-1949
    - Pool, Mrs. Sydney H. (Annie E. Alexander Pool, mother-in-law), 1933-1947
    - Poole, Elizabeth (sister), 1937-1946
    - Snowden, Lois Arnold and Ernest (daughter and son-in-law)
      - 1934-1944, (4 folders)
      - 1945-1950, undated, (6 folders) (Box 2, Reel 2)
  - Newspaper clippings, 1947
- Journals and Notebooks, circa 1908-1946 (Box 2-3, Reel 2-3)
  Journals, notebooks, notes, and typescripts of notes primarily documenting Arnold's trips and conferences.
  Arranged chronologically.
  - circa 1908-circa 1918, notebook with financial accounts (Box 2, Reel 2)
  - 1918, Sept.-Dec., trip to England
  - 1941
    - Apr.-May, trip to England
    - July-Aug., Roosevelt-Churchill Conference, Placentia Bay, Newfoundland
  - 1942
    - May-June, trip to England
    - Sept.-Oct., trip to southwest Pacific
  - 1943
    - Jan.-Feb., trip to North Africa and China
    - Aug.-Sept., trip to England